<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.nl" -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" xml:lang="en" consensus="yes" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-aname-03">
<?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes"?><?rfc compact="yes"?><?rfc subcompact="no"?><?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="ANAME">Address-specific DNS aliases (ANAME)</title><author initials="T." surname="Finch" fullname="Tony Finch"><organization>University of Cambridge</organization><address><postal><street></street>
<street>University Information Services</street>
<street>Roger Needham Building</street>
<street>7 JJ Thomson Avenue</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<code>CB3 0RB</code>
<country>England</country>
</postal><email>dot@dotat.at</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="E." surname="Hunt" fullname="Evan Hunt"><organization>ISC</organization><address><postal><street>950 Charter St</street>
<city>Redwood City</city>
<code>94063</code>
<country>USA</country>
<region>CA</region>
</postal><email>each@isc.org</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="P.D." surname="van Dijk" fullname="Peter van Dijk"><organization abbrev="PowerDNS">PowerDNS.COM B.V.</organization><address><postal><street></street>
<city>Den Haag</city>
<country>The Netherlands</country>
</postal><email>peter.van.dijk@powerdns.com</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="A." surname="Eden" fullname="Anthony Eden"><organization>DNSimple</organization><address><postal><street></street>
<city>Boston</city>
<code>USA</code>
<region>MA</region>
</postal><email>anthony.eden@dnsimple.com</email>
<uri>https://dnsimple.com/</uri>
</address></author>
<author initials="W.M." surname="Mekking" fullname="Matthijs Mekking"><organization>ISC</organization><address><postal><street>950 Charter St</street>
<city>Redwood City</city>
<code>94063</code>
<country>USA</country>
<region>CA</region>
</postal><email>matthijs@isc.org</email>
</address></author>
<date year="2019" month="April" day="15"></date>
<area>Operations and Management</area><workgroup>DNS Operations</workgroup><keyword>DNS</keyword>
<keyword>RR</keyword>
<keyword>ANAME</keyword>
<keyword>CNAME</keyword>
<keyword>apex</keyword>

<abstract><t>This document defines the &quot;ANAME&quot; DNS RR type, to provide similar
functionality to CNAME, but only for type A and AAAA queries. Unlike
CNAME, an ANAME can coexist with other record types. The ANAME RR
allows zone owners to make an apex domain name into an alias in a
standards compliant manner.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>It can be desirable to provide web sites (and other services) at a
bare domain name (such as <spanx style="verb">example.com</spanx>) as well as a service-specific
subdomain (<spanx style="verb">www.example.com</spanx>).</t>
<t>If the web site is hosted by a third-party provider, the ideal way to
provision its name in the DNS is using a CNAME record, so that the
third party provider retains control over the mapping from names to IP
address(es). It is now common for name-to-address mappings to be
highly dynamic, dependent on client location, server load, etc.</t>
<t>However, CNAME records cannot coexist with other records with the same
owner name. (The reason why is explored in <xref target="history"></xref>). This restriction
means they cannot appear at a zone apex (such as <spanx style="verb">example.com</spanx>) because of
the SOA, NS, and other records that have to be present there. CNAME records
can also conflict at subdomains, for example, if <spanx style="verb">department.example.edu</spanx>
has separately hosted mail and web servers.</t>
<t>Redirecting website lookups to an alternate domain name via SRV or URI
resource records would be an effective solution from the DNS point of
view, but to date, browser vendors have not accepted this approach.</t>
<t>As a result, the only widely supported and standards-compliant way to
publish a web site at a bare domain is to place A and/or AAAA records
at the zone apex. The flexibility afforded by CNAME is not available.</t>
<t>This document specifies a new RR type &quot;ANAME&quot;, which provides similar
functionality to CNAME, but only for address queries (i.e., for type A
or AAAA). The basic idea is that the address records next to an ANAME
record are automatically copied from and kept in sync with the ANAME
target's address records. The ANAME record can be present at any DNS
node, and can coexist with most other RR types, enabling it to be
present at a zone apex, or any other name where the presence of other
records prevents the use of a CNAME record.</t>
<t>Similar authoritative functionality has been implemented and deployed
by a number of DNS software vendors and service providers, using names
such as ALIAS, ANAME, apex CNAME, CNAME flattening, and top-level
redirection. These mechanisms are proprietary, which hinders the
ability of zone owners to have the same data served from multiple
providers or to move from one provider to another. None of these
proprietary implementations includes a mechanism for resolvers to
follow the redirection chain themselves.</t>

<section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
<t>The core functionality of this mechanism allows zone
administrators to start using ANAME records unilaterally, without
requiring secondary servers or resolvers to be upgraded.</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The resource record definition in <xref target="rdata"></xref> is intended to provide
zone data portability between standards-compliant DNS servers and
the common core functionality of existing proprietary
ANAME-like facilities.</t>
<t>The zone maintenance mechanism described in <xref target="primary"></xref> keeps the
ANAME's sibling address records in sync with the ANAME target.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>This definition is enough to be useful by itself. However, it can be less
than optimal in certain situations: for instance, when the ANAME target uses
clever tricks to provide different answers to different clients to
improve latency or load balancing.</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The Additional section processing rules in <xref target="additional"></xref> inform
resolvers that an ANAME record is in play.</t>
<t>Resolvers can use this ANAME information as described in
<xref target="resolver"></xref> to obtain answers that are tailored to the resolver
rather than to the zone's primary master.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Resolver support for ANAME is not necessary, since ANAME-oblivious
resolvers can get working answers from authoritative servers. It's
just an optimization that can be rolled out incrementally, and that
will help ANAME to work better the more widely it is deployed.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>An &quot;address record&quot; is a DNS resource record whose type is A or AAAA.
These are referred to as &quot;address types&quot;. &quot;Address query&quot; refers to a
DNS query for any address type.</t>
<t>When talking about &quot;address records&quot; we mean the entire RRset,
including owner name and TTL. We treat missing address records (i.e.
NXDOMAIN or NODATA) the same successfully resolving as a set of zero
address records, and distinct from &quot;failure&quot; which covers error
responses such as SERVFAIL or REFUSED.</t>
<t>The &quot;sibling address records&quot; of an ANAME record are the address
records at the same owner name as the ANAME, which are subject to
ANAME substitution.</t>
<t>The &quot;target address records&quot; of an ANAME record are the address
records obtained by resolving the ultimate target of the ANAME (see
<xref target="subst"></xref>).</t>
<t>Other DNS-related terminology can be found in
<xref target="RFC8499"></xref>.</t>
<t>The key words MUST, MUST NOT, REQUIRED, SHALL,
SHALL NOT, SHOULD, SHOULD NOT, RECOMMENDED, MAY,
and OPTIONAL in this document are to be interpreted as described in
<xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="rdata" title="The ANAME resource record">
<t>This document defines the &quot;ANAME&quot; DNS resource record type, with RR TYPE
value [TBD].</t>

<section anchor="presentation-and-wire-format" title="Presentation and wire format">
<t>The ANAME presentation format is identical to that of CNAME <xref target="RFC1033"></xref>:</t>

<figure><artwork>    owner ttl class ANAME target
</artwork></figure>

<t>The wire format is also identical to CNAME <xref target="RFC1035"></xref>, except that
name compression is not permitted in ANAME RDATA, per <xref target="RFC3597"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="coexistence" title="Coexistence with other types">
<t>Only one ANAME &lt;target&gt; can be defined per &lt;owner&gt;. An ANAME
RRset MUST NOT contain more than one resource record.</t>
<t>An ANAME's sibling address records are under the control of ANAME
processing (see <xref target="primary"></xref>) and are not first-class records in their
own right. They MAY exist in zone files, but they can subsequently be
altered by ANAME processing.</t>
<t>ANAME records MAY freely coexist at the same owner name with other RR
types, except they MUST NOT coexist with CNAME or any other RR type
that restricts the types with which it can itself coexist. That means
ANAME records can coexist at the same owner name with A and AAAA records.
These are the sibling address records that are updated with the target
addresses that are retrieved through the ANAME substitution
process <xref target="subst"></xref>.</t>
<t>Like other types, ANAME records can coexist with DNAME records at the
same owner name; in fact, the two can be used cooperatively to
redirect both the owner name address records (via ANAME) and everything
under it (via DNAME).</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="subst" title="Substituting ANAME sibling address records">
<t>This process is used by both primary masters (see <xref target="primary"></xref>) and
resolvers (see <xref target="resolver"></xref>), though they vary in how they apply the
edit described in the final step.</t>
<t>The following steps MUST be performed for each address type:</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>Starting at the ANAME owner, follow the chain of ANAME and/or
CNAME records as far as possible to find the ultimate target.</t>
<t>If a loop is detected, continue with an empty RRset, otherwise get
the ultimate target's address records. (Ignore any sibling address
records of intermediate ANAMEs.)</t>
<t>Stop if resolution failed. (Note that NXDOMAIN and NODATA count as
successfully resolving an empty RRset.)</t>
<t>If one ore more address records are found, replace the owner of
the target address records with the owner of the ANAME record.
Reduce the TTL to match the ANAME record if it is greater. Drop any
RRSIG records.</t>
<t>Stop if this modified RRset is the same as the sibling RRset
(ignoring any RRSIG records). The comparison MAY treat
nearly-equal TTLs as the same.</t>
<t>Delete the sibling address RRset (if any) and replace it with the
modified RRset.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>At this point, the substituted RRset is not signed. A primary master
will proceed to sign the substituted RRset, whereas resolvers can only
use the substituted RRset when an unsigned answer is appropriate. This
is explained in more detail in the following sections.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="primary" title="ANAME processing by primary masters">
<t>Each ANAME's sibling address records are kept up-to-date as if by the
following process, for each address type:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Perform ANAME sibling address record substitution as described in
<xref target="subst"></xref>. Any edit performed in the final step is applied to the
ANAME's zone. A primary server MAY use Dynamic Updates (DNS UPDATE)
<xref target="RFC2136"></xref> to update the zone.</t>
<t>If resolution failed, wait for a period before trying again. This
retry time SHOULD be configurable.</t>
<t>Otherwise, wait until the target address RRset TTL has expired or
is close to expiring, then repeat.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>It may be more efficient to manage the polling per ANAME target rather
than per ANAME as specified (for example if the same ANAME target is
used by multiple zones).</t>
<t>Sibling address records are committed to the zone and stored in
nonvolatile storage. This allows a server to restart without delays
due to ANAME processing, use offline DNSSEC signing, and not implement
special ANAME processing logic when handling a DNS query.</t>
<t><xref target="alternatives"></xref> describes how ANAME would fit in different DNS
architectures that use online signing or tailored responses.</t>

<section anchor="zone-transfers" title="Zone transfers">
<t>ANAME is no more special than any other RRtype and does not introduce
any special processing related to zone transfers.</t>
<t>A zone containing ANAME records that point to frequently-changing
targets will itself change frequently, and may see an increased number
of zone transfers.  Or if a very large number of zones are sharing the
same ANAME target, and that changes address, that may cause a great
volume of zone transfers.  Guidance on dealing with ANAME in large scale
implementations is provided <xref target="alternatives"></xref>.</t>
<t>Secondary servers that rely on zone transfers to obtain sibling
address records, just like the rest of the zone, and serve them in the
usual way (with <xref target="additional"></xref> Additional section processing if they
support it). A working DNS NOTIFY <xref target="RFC1996"></xref> setup is recommended to
avoid extra delays propagating updated sibling address records when
they change.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="dnssec" title="DNSSEC">
<t>A zone containing ANAME records that will update A and AAAA records
has to do so before signing the zone with DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033"></xref>
<xref target="RFC4034"></xref> <xref target="RFC4035"></xref>.</t>
<t>DNSSEC signatures on sibling address records are generated in the same
way as for normal (dynamic) updates.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ttls" title="TTLs">
<t>Sibling address records are served from authoritative servers with a
fixed TTL. Normally this TTL is expected to be the same as the target
address records' TTL (or the ANAME TTL if that is smaller); however
the exact mechanism for obtaining the target is unspecified, so cache
effects or deliberate policies might make the sibling TTL smaller.
There is a more extended discussion of TTL handling in {#ttls}.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="resolver" title="ANAME processing by resolvers">
<t>When a resolver makes an address query in the usual way, it might
receive a response containing ANAME information in the additional
section, as described in <xref target="additional"></xref>. This informs the resolver
that it MAY resolve the ANAME target address records to get answers that
are tailored to the resolver rather than the ANAME's primary master.
It SHOULD include the target address records in the Additional section
of its responses as described in <xref target="additional"></xref>.</t>
<t>In order to provide tailored answers to clients that are
ANAME-oblivious, the resolver MAY perform sibling address record
substitution in the following situations:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The resolver's client queries with DO=0. (As discussed in
<xref target="security-considerations"></xref>, if the resolver finds it would
downgrade a secure answer to insecure, it MAY choose not to
substitute the sibling address records.)</t>
<t>The resolver's client queries with DO=1 and the ANAME and sibling
address records are unsigned. (Note that this situation does not apply
when the records are signed but insecure: the resolver might not be
able to validate them because of a broken chain of trust, but its
client could have an extra trust anchor that does allow it to validate
them; if the resolver substitutes the sibling address records they will
become bogus.)</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In these first two cases, the resolver MAY perform ANAME sibling
address record substitution as described in <xref target="subst"></xref>. Any edit
performed in the final step is applied to the Answer section of the
response. The resolver SHOULD then perform Additional section processing
as described in <xref target="additional"></xref>.</t>
<t>If the resolver's client is querying using an API such as
<spanx style="verb">getaddrinfo</spanx> <xref target="RFC3493"></xref> that does not support DNSSEC validation, the
resolver MAY perform ANAME sibling address record substitution as
described in <xref target="subst"></xref>. Any edits performed in the final step are
applied to the addresses returned by the API. (This case is for
validating stub resolvers that query an upstream recursive server with
DO=1, so they cannot rely on the recursive server to do ANAME
substitution for them.)</t>
</section>

<section anchor="additional" title="Additional section processing">

<section anchor="authoritative-servers" title="Authoritative servers">

<section anchor="address-queries" title="Address queries">
<t>When a server receives an address query for a name that has an ANAME
record, the response's Additional section MUST contain the ANAME record.
The ANAME record indicates to a client that it might wish to resolve
the target address records itself.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="aname-queries" title="ANAME queries">
<t>When a server receives an query for type ANAME, there are two
possibilities:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The query resolved to an ANAME record; any sibling address records
SHOULD be added to the Additional section.</t>
<t>The query did not resolve to an ANAME record; any address records
with the same owner name SHOULD be added to the Additional section
of the NOERROR response.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The sibling address records MAY be already substituted.</t>
<t>When adding address records to the Additional section, if not all
address types are present and the zone is signed, the server SHOULD
include a DNSSEC proof of nonexistence for the missing address types.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="resolvers" title="Resolvers">

<section anchor="address-queries-1" title="Address queries">
<t>When a resolver receives an address query for a name that has an ANAME
record, the response's Additional section:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>MUST contain the ANAME record;</t>
<t>MAY contain the target address records that match the query
type (or the corresponding proof of nonexistence), if they are
available in the cache and the target address RDATA fields differ
from the sibling address RRset.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="aname-queries-1" title="ANAME queries">
<t>When a resolver receives an query for type ANAME, there are three
possibilities:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>The query resolved to an ANAME record, and the resolver has the
target address records; any target address records SHOULD be added
to the Additional section.</t>
<t>The query resolved to an ANAME record, and the resolver does not
have the target address records; any sibling address records
SHOULD be added to the Additional section.</t>
<t>The query did not resolve to an ANAME record; any address records
with the same owner name SHOULD be added to the Additional section
of the NOERROR response.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Just like with an authoritative server, when adding address records to
the Additional section, if not all address types are present and the
zone is signed, the server SHOULD include a DNSSEC proof of nonexistence
for the missing address types.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA considerations">
<t>IANA is requested to assign a DNS RR TYPE value for ANAME resource
records under the &quot;Resource Record (RR) TYPEs&quot; subregistry under the
&quot;Domain Name System (DNS) Parameters&quot; registry.</t>
<t>IANA might wish to consider the creation of a registry of address types;
addition of new types to such a registry would then implicitly update
this specification.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security considerations">
<t>When a primary master updates an ANAME's sibling address records to
match its target address records, it uses its own best information
as to the correct answer. The primary master might sign the updated
records, but that is not a guarantee of the actual correctness
of the answer. This signing can have the effect of promoting an insecure
response from the ANAME &lt;target&gt; to a signed response from the
&lt;owner&gt;, which can then appear to clients to be more trustworthy
than it should. DNSSEC validation SHOULD be used when resolving the
ANAME &lt;target&gt; to mitigate this possible harm. Primary masters MAY
refuse to substitute ANAME sibling address records unless the
&lt;target&gt; node is both signed and validated.</t>
<t>When a resolver substitutes an ANAME's sibling address records, it can
find that the sibling address records are secure but the target
address records are insecure. Going ahead with the substitution will
downgrade a secure answer to an insecure one. However this is likely to be
the counterpart of the situation described in the previous paragraph,
so the resolver is downgrading an answer that the ANAME's primary
master upgraded. A resolver will only downgrade an answer in this way
when its client is security-oblivious; however the client's path to
the resolver is likely to be practically safer than the resolver's
path to the ANAME target's servers. Resolvers MAY choose not to
substitute sibling address records when they are more secure than the
target address records.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
<t>Thanks to Mark Andrews, Ray Bellis, Stefan Buehler, Paul Ebersman,
Richard Gibson, Tatuya JINMEI, Hakan Lindqvist, Mattijs Mekking,
Stephen Morris, Bjorn Mott, Richard Salts, Mukund Sivaraman, Job
Snijders, Jan Vcelak, Paul Vixie, Duane Wessels, and Paul Wouters,
Olli Vanhoja for discussion and feedback.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="changes-since-the-last-revision" title="Changes since the last revision">
<t>[This section is to be removed before publication as an RFC.]</t>
<t>The full history of this draft and its issue tracker can be found at
<eref target="https://github.com/each/draft-aname">https://github.com/each/draft-aname</eref></t>

<section anchor="version-04" title="Version -04">
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Split up section about Additional Section processing.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="version-03" title="Version -03">
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Grammar improvements (Olli Vanhoja)</t>
<t>Split up Implications section, clarify text on zone transfers
and dynamic updates.</t>
<t>Rewrite Alternative setup section and move to Appendix, add
text on zone transfer scalibility concerns and GeoIP.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="version-02" title="Version -02">
<t>Major revamp, so authoritative servers (other than primary masters)
now do not do any special ANAME processing, just Additional section
processing.</t>
</section>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3597.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2136.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1033.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml"?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1996.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3493.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0973.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0882.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2308.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2065.xml"?>
</references>

<section anchor="implementation-status" title="Implementation status">
<t>PowerDNS currently implements a similar authoritative-only feature
using &quot;ALIAS&quot; records, which are expanded by the primary server and
transfered as address records to secondaries.</t>
<t>[TODO: Add discussion of DNSimple, DNS Made Easy, EasyDNS, Cloudflare, Amazon,
Dyn, and Akamai.]</t>
</section>

<section anchor="history" title="Historical note">
<t>In the early DNS <xref target="RFC0882"></xref>, CNAME records were allowed to coexist
with other records. However this led to coherency problems: if a
resolver had no cache entries for a given name, it would resolve
queries for un-cached records at that name in the usual way; once it
had cached a CNAME record for a name, it would resolve queries for
un-cached records using CNAME target instead.</t>
<t>For example, given the zone contents below, the original CNAME
behaviour meant that if you asked for <spanx style="verb">alias.example.com TXT</spanx> first,
you would get the answer &quot;owner&quot;, but if you asked for
<spanx style="verb">alias.example.com A</spanx> then <spanx style="verb">alias.example.com TXT</spanx> you would get the
answer &quot;target&quot;.</t>

<figure><artwork>   alias.example.com.      TXT    &quot;owner&quot;
   alias.example.com.      CNAME  canonical.example.com.
   canonical.example.com.  TXT    &quot;target&quot;
   canonical.example.com.  A      192.0.2.1
</artwork></figure>

<t>This coherency problem was fixed in <xref target="RFC0973"></xref> which introduced the
inconvenient rule that a CNAME acts as an alias for all other RR types
at a name, which prevents the coexistence of CNAME with other records.</t>
<t>A better fix might have been to improve the cache's awareness of which
records do and do not coexist with a CNAME record. However that would
have required a negative cache mechanism which was not added to the
DNS until later <xref target="RFC1034"></xref> <xref target="RFC2308"></xref>.</t>
<t>While <xref target="RFC2065"></xref> relaxed the restriction by allowing coexistence of
CNAME with DNSSEC records, this exception is still not applicable to
other resource records. RRSIG and NSEC exist to prove the integrity of
the CNAME record; they are not intended to associate arbitrary data
with the domain name. DNSSEC records avoid interoperability problems
by being largely invisible to security-oblivious resolvers.</t>
<t>Now that the DNS has negative caching, it is tempting to amend the
algorithm for resolving with CNAME records to allow them to coexist
with other types. Although an amended resolver will be compatible with
the rest of the DNS, it will not be of much practical use because
authoritative servers which rely on coexisting CNAMEs will not
interoperate well with older resolvers. Practical experiments show
that the problems are particularly acute when CNAME and MX try to
coexist.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ttls-1" title="On preserving TTLs">
<t>An ANAME's sibling address records are in an unusual situation: they
are authoritative data in the owner's zone, so from that point of view
the owner has the last say over what their TTL should be; on the other
hand, ANAMEs are supposed to act as aliases, in which case the target
should control the address record TTLs.</t>
<t>However there are some technical constraints that make it difficult to
preserve the target address record TTLs.</t>
<t>The following subsections conclude that the end-to-end TTL
(from the authoritative servers for the target address records to
end-user DNS caches) should be set as the target address record TTL plus the
sibling address record TTL.</t>
<t>[MM: Discuss: I think it should be just the ANAME record TTL perhaps
the minimum of ANAME and sibling address RRset TTL. We should provide
some guidance on TTL settings for ANAME).</t>
<t>[TF: see issue #30]</t>

<section anchor="query-bunching" title="Query bunching">
<t>If the times of end-user queries for a domain name are well
distributed, then (typically) queries received by the authoritative
servers for that domain are also well distributed. If the domain is
popular, a recursive server will re-query for it once every TTL
seconds, but the periodic queries from all the various recursive
servers will not be aligned, so the queries remain well distributed.</t>
<t>However, imagine that the TTLs of an ANAME's sibling address records
are decremented in the same way as cache entries in recursive servers.
Then all the recursive servers querying for the name would try to
refresh their caches at the same time when the TTL reaches zero. They
would become synchronized, and all the queries for the domain would be
bunched into periodic spikes.</t>
<t>This specification says that ANAME sibling address records have a
normal fixed TTL derived from (e.g. equal or nearly equal to) the
target address records' original TTL. There is no cache-like
decrementing TTL, so there is no bunching of queries.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="upstream-caches" title="Upstream caches">
<t>There are two straightforward ways to get an RRset's original TTL:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>by directly querying an authoritative server;</t>
<t>using the original TTL field from the RRset's RRGIG record(s).</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>However, not all zones are signed, and a primary master might not be
able to query other authoritative servers directly (e.g. if it is a
hidden primary behind a strict firewall). Instead it might have to
obtain an ANAME's target address records via some other recursive
server.</t>
<t>Querying via a separate recursive server means the primary master
cannot trivially obtain the target address records' original TTLs.
Fortunately this is likely to be a self-correcting problem for similar
reasons to the query-bunching discussed in the previous subsection.
The primary master re-checks the target address records just after the
TTL expires when its upstream cache has just refreshed them, so the
TTL will be nearly equal to the original TTL.</t>
<t>A related consideration is that the primary master cannot in general
refresh its copies of an ANAME's target address records more
frequently than their TTL, without privileged control over its
resolver cache.</t>
<t>Combined with the requirement that sibling address records are served
with a fixed TTL, this means that the end-to-end TTL will be the
target address record TTL (which determines when the sibling address
records are updated) plus the sibling address record TTL (which
determines when end-user caches are updated).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="aname-chains" title="ANAME chains">
<t>ANAME sibling address record substitution is made slightly more
complicated by the requirement to follow chains of ANAME and/or CNAME
records. This stops the end-to-end TTL from being inflated by each
ANAME in the chain.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ttls-and-zone-transfers" title="TTLs and zone transfers">
<t>When things are working properly (with secondary name servers
responding to NOTIFY messages promptly) the authoritative servers will
follow changes to ANAME target address records according to their
TTLs. As a result the end-to-end TTL is unchanged from the previous
subsection.</t>
<t>If NOTIFY doesn't work, the TTLs can be stretched by the zone's SOA
refresh timer. More serious breakage can stretch them up to the zone
expiry time.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="answer-vs-additional-sections" title="Answer vs Additional sections">
<t>[MM: Discuss what should be in the additional section: ANAME makes
sense, but differs from CNAME logic (where the CNAME is in the answer
section). Additional target records that match the query type in my
opinion should go in the answer section. Additional target address
records that do not match the query type can go in the additional
section].</t>
<t>[TF: from experience with DNAME I think there's a risk of interop
problems if we put unexpected records in the answer section, so I said
everything should go in additional. We'll expand this appendix to
explain the rationale.]</t>
</section>

<section anchor="alternatives" title="Alternative setups">
<t>If you are a large scale DNS provider, ANAME may introduce some
scalability concerns.  A frequently changing ANAME target, or a
ANAME target that changes its address and is used for many zones,
can lead to an increased number of zone transfers.  Such DNS
architectures may want to consider a zone transfer mechanism
outside the DNS.</t>
<t>Another way to deal with zone transfer scalability is to move the
ANAME processing (<xref target="subst"></xref>) inside the name server daemon. This is
not a requirement for ANAME to work, but may be a better solution
in large scale implementations.  These implementations usually
already rely on online DNSSEC signing for similar reasons.  If
ANAME processing occurs inside the name server daemon, it MUST be
done before any DNSSEC online signing happens.</t>
<t>For example, some existing ANAME-like implementations are based on
a DNS server architecture, in which a zone's published authoritative
servers all perform the duties of a primary master in a distributed
manner: provisioning records from a non-DNS back-end store,
refreshing DNSSEC signatures, and so forth.  They don't use standard
standard zone transfers, and already implement their ANAME-like
processing inside the name server daemon, substituting ANAME sibling
address records on demand.</t>
<t>Also, some DNS providers will tailor responses based on information
in the client request.  Such implementations will use the source IP
address or EDNS Client Subnet information and use geographical data
(GeoIP) or network latency measurements to decide what the best
answer is for a given query.  Such setups won't work with
traditional DNSSEC and provide DNSSEC support usually through online
signing.  Similar such setups should provide ANAME support through
substituting ANAME sibling records on demand.</t>
<t>The exact mechanism for obtaining the target address records in such
setups is unspecified; typically they will be resolved in the DNS in
the usual way, but if an ANAME implementation has special knowledge
of the target it can short-cut the substitution process, or it can
use clever tricks such as client-dependant answers.</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
